<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mutiny maintained: or, Sedition made good from its [brace] unity, knowledge, wit, government. Being a discourse, directed to the Armies information.</title>
            <author>N. N.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N46</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E774_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207290</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866349</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866349</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 118:E774[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mutiny maintained: or, Sedition made good from its [brace] unity, knowledge, wit, government. Being a discourse, directed to the Armies information.</title>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>P. 2 signed: N.N.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 3. 1659".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sedition --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118620:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MUTINY MAINTAINED: OR, SEDITION Made good from Its
<list>
                  <item>Unity,</item>
                  <item>Knowledge,</item>
                  <item>Wit,</item>
                  <item>Government.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>BEING A DISCOURSE, directed to the ARMIES INFORMATION.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118620:2"/>
            <head>To the Ingenuous Souldiery.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Maſters,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU are now in your Winter Quarters; I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſent you this Pamphlet to warm you. Not that I intend to play at Blow-coals with you, you know that ſport too well. Only, finding your Genius given to new Doctrines (many of you being Seekers) I thought a Paradox might not not be unwelcome, one allowes killing, another lying; ſuch Treatiſes every foot come to your hands; ſure then you will accept of this Piece; that ſmells much of your Match and Gunpowder, and concerns more your Strength, and your Trade. I have no Stratagem to take you, but reaſon; and if you exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Diſcourſe to the pith, not ſuperficially, I doubt not but you will ſubmit to him, that</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>wiſhes you as he doth himſelf. N. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118620:2"/>
            <p>THey that have ſeen the Dancing Horſe, how exactly he knows his Figures, and keeps Time to the Muſick, as if a <hi>French</hi> Dancing Maſter had taught him. How he counts money, as if he had been a Caſh keeper. How he ſcrapes, and makes legs, and kneels for the King, as if he begd his enjoyment, but for the State pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently lyes down and groans: they all admire, and cry, This Horſe ſhews tricks that youl'd believe the Beaſt were Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; which means no mor then this, That he truly hath not Reaſon, but reſembles only him that hath. So <hi>Tacitus</hi> writes of the Legions in <hi>Germany</hi> mutining, That they would now be all on fire, and anon be all as quiet, with ſo great equality and conſtancy that youl'd believe they were well Govern'd, which is as much to ſay, That they ſeem'd govern'd, but in truth were not.</p>
            <p>Now I will endeavour to make it clear againſt the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, That Sedition, or let it be the Seditious multitude, is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd perfectly by its own Nature, much more then any obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Army can be: Which I thus argue;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vnity. </seg>
               </label> Since Bodies compounded of diſtinct Members and Parts, ſuch as are Cities, Armies or Clocks, hence come to boaſt of their Unity. How much more ſhall theſe accoſt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to true and proper Unity, that are made up of like Parts, and maintained in their Order from a like Principle? Now if you will examine the occaſions and Unities of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, ſurely it will appear, and you muſt confeſs, That a Seditious body is better governed then another made up of divers parts. But becauſe no leſs to the Civil then to the Military the name of Sedition is given, not to go from my Text whereof <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpeaks, I will confine my ſelf only to the Military. This then as much as the name teaches, is nothing elſe, then a Separation of one part of the Army from the reſt of the Body on purpoſe to obtain by force ſomething from the the Commander. Now, if 'tis ſaid of an obedient Army (and tis well ſaid) That it is Governed, when upon the Word given, being put in order, it preſently joyns Battel with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy: Much more ought we to ſay it (if we compare one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118620:3"/>with the other) of the Seditious. Let's come to the proof up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on trace of ſome Maxims.</p>
            <p>The efficient cauſe of an Army may be entituled the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, for as Order is the ſoul or form of that Army, ſuch Order comes produced from no other then the General, who like an Idaea contains it. A Seditious Body too hath a Commander that will excellently govern it, becauſe it will yield moſt eaſily to be governed, being all of one mind like him they have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; and much more, becauſe their own good is the very ſame with the good of the Commander: A thing not ordinary betwixt the Army and the General. See <hi>Alexander</hi> conducting his <hi>Macedons</hi> through unknown, untamed and unpenetrable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; think you an equal profit accru'd to his Phalanges or Squadrons, as did to him? Surely no: He counted all their ſufferings Little, becauſe by them he became Great: his ſmall Body valued it not, ſo he might obtain the great World. For all their hungers and thirſts the unhoſpitable Rocks found his Tent furniſht with exquiſite Meats, and generous Wine to crown his goblets: whoſe bottoms being carved with the like Effigies of thoſe conquered Kings he took in his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, he delighted ſtill to drink them empty, more to tickle his Ambition then to quench his Thirſt. No, twas not ſo with his Souldiers; they Dyed to Immortalize him, and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Plains with their own Limbs, that he might reap the Palms thence budding. One only was in Purple, for which a thouſand wounded; one only Triumphing, for which a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Conquering. To Win only for him, they Loſt not only their own, but themſelves.</p>
            <p>Hence from not being the ſame, the good of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and the Souldiers, it ariſes, That though the final cauſe of him and them Unitely taken, may be called the very ſame, that is, the Victory; yet for all that, both the one and the others ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by themſelves, are drawn by ends too much differing one from another; whence after is derived that diſcordance of Cauſes, which is contrary (as I ſaid before) to the regulating of a thing which ought to be governed.</p>
            <p>I ſhould loſe the day in wearying the Army, if I would go to ſhew by examples how differing the motives of Souldiers are in fighting: not with the Commander only, but compar'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118620:3"/>amongſt themſelves: Some brandiſh the Sword, not to win glory, but to gain gold. Others with an immoderate force weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens all the interprize; and to make himſelf the only one among them, comes to divide them. Others, only make ſtand, and face the enemy, becauſe he is too ſtrong behind their back, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannor flie, try to put him to ſlight. This man ſeeks not renown with his ſword upon the Foe, but his revenge upon a particular Enemy. Some deſtine their luſt to anothers wife, and for the plunder of a tender maid, value not the loſs of the whole Baggage. Avarize, Zeal, Diſdain, Fear, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Luſt, Rage and Raſhneſs, make a hundred factions of one Army. Elſe why do we read of <hi>Pompey</hi> for to animate his men, to run up and down, now comforting theſe with promiſes, then pricking them with reproof; now ſtirring up their hopes, then provoking their vigilance with the danger; ſometimes enflaming their covetouſneſs, with ſhewing the great booty in the adverſs Camp; then awaking their compaſſion, by telling of the miſery of their Country. Sure all this becauſe he knew there muſt needs be diverſe arguments to perſwade the ſame action to many, that have divers ends in the working it.</p>
            <p>Now in a Mutiny the parts are all alike, as in a train of gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, if in a moment but one ſpark fall upon one corn, it ſets fire on all, and runs to the very end, for no other cauſe, but that they are all alike. So the firſt will that flaſhes or gives fire in a Sedition, becomes at once the will to a thouſand breſts. Such is the conſanguinity and kindred of Minds! And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it muſt be ſo upon good reaſon, ſince the fear of the ſame Puniſhment, and the hopes of the ſame reward binds them in an undiſſolvable Tie. They will the ſame thing, becauſe there lives but one heart in many breaſts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Knwoledg. </seg>
               </label> But unity alone is not our argument, there are a number of other reaſons ſpeaking for us, as thus; Who ſights, will he not govern himſelf the better againſt the eneny, the more that he hath a perfect <hi>Knowledg</hi> of that Enemy? Surely yes. Now by whom is he beſt known, by an Army in the day of Battel, or by this Seditious body in the Quarrel? The Army oft fights againſt people of contrary Climates and Cuſtoms, and knows not whether their Flights be for Feare or for Stratagem; whether their Charges be out of Election or Neceſſity; or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118620:4"/>their preparations be in reality or appearance. Again, though the conditions and natures of the Souldier were cleerly known, yet on the other ſide how oft doth the way and nature of the Commander happen to be obſcure, who, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that name, ought to order it ſo, that to his own ſhirt even his own thoughts muſt be concealed? It will happen then almoſt impoſſible for that Army to be well governed, when neither it, nor he that governs it, hath any knowledg of the enemies, or of their Captain.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the enemy of a mutinuous body is as it were alwayes the very ſame, which before the ſedition was its Commander, that is to ſay, tis that, of whom by often and oft repeated proofs they know where are the ſtrengths, where the defects; on what ſide they are moſt expoſ'd, or moſt impenetrable upon aſſaults of others, whether there be matter of ſurprize, or of force. So for the Commander they mutiny againſt; they know his courage by many tryals in charges, his ſuffering in ſieges, his fortune in fights, and his diſcipline in his rigidneſs. Certainly, theſe that were well governed by him, are beſt of all taught to govern themſelves againſt him: Eſpecially, ſince mutinies happen for the moſt on that part of the Army, which the Commander knows beſt of all the reſt, that is to ſay, that part which is compounded of old Souldiers, becauſe they among all the reſt are highly ſtrong and ingenious, and well knowing to themſelves of their abilities to pretend to great things, and to complain with much juſtice, not obtaining conditions, which is no leſs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in moving ſeditions, then uſeful to be known in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards governing them, as tis fit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Wit. </seg>
               </label> But to paſs by the knowledg and courage of the Old Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, who hath defied well nigh a thouſand deaths to make his Commander glorious by his ſcars, give me leave for a witneſs of the third condition, which is Wit, to bring into the Field one Pretty proof hinted me by <hi>Tacitus,</hi> who tells, that <hi>Germanicus</hi> whilſt he made the Pile and Conqueſt of <hi>France,</hi> hearing of the ſeditious riſing in his Armies in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſwiftly in all haſt marches th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther to quiet them. At this ſuddain flaſh of his imperial look (which ſerenely lightning made them to love him whilſt he terrify'd them)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118620:4"/>the ſeditious troops with humbled and relenting browes gave great ſignals of their repentance; nevertheleſs, ſo ſoon as he was enterd the Tents, they ſet up a cry, and ſnatching by force his right hand, under a ſhew of kiſſing it, thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit Souldiers wrought ſo, that he muſt feel their empty and disſurniſht jawes with his own fingers. <hi>Cicero</hi> here with all his flame colours to figure out the motion of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo ſtir'd up, cannot ſpeak ſo much, nor ſo lively, as was ſaid by theſe pale and trembling lips in this their ſilence, who not being able to bite the hands, they embowelled themſelves into the marrow and midſt of their Generals heart. And thus was heard the dumb to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>When never ſhall it be granted, O good <hi>Germanicus,</hi> to repoſe, till our ſepulcral ages obtain us our repoſe? Our jaws make witneſs what advances we are like to draw from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wars, and ſhall it not be permitted us, after we have loſt our bones, to lay up in ſafety the miſerable relicks of our body? What neceſſity ſo hard forces wretched mortals to live amongſt deaths, even until death? See now our ſtooping ſhoulders can bear no longer our weighty armes. See our dry hands, that infect our pikes with their palſie, can do no more then joyn themſelves in putting up ſupplicant deſires to thy mercy and compaſſion. Thus to be obſtinate to command heavy ſhadowes, rather living bodies under thy banners, is nothing elſe but an ingenious ambition not to make bloody fights, no, though we miſerably ſhould be cut all in pieces. Ah, grant us the dominion of our life, at leaſt, in a ſeaſon when we are to loſe it; ſecure that to us, when it can no longer ſecure thee. Is there no other death, but the Sword, poſſibly under the Romans? Thy Army will not be enerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though it be not accompanyed with our falling age, which tires it ſelf in following it. The body will be the ſtronger, if the wither'd Members be cut off for unprofitable. This our deſire is the effect of a moſt happy Fortune, thy Partiſan: She will not be expoſ'd to the long carreer of thy noble toils and enterprizes, which ſhe foreſees, unleſs firſt in the place of thy worn Souldiers, you ſublitute and enroll freſh, young, and luſty.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118620:5"/>
            <p>Now lets believe, if Wit knows to arm ſo ſtrongly the diſarmed mouths of the ſeditious with a ſilent eloquence, for to gain the good will of their Captain; it will alſo know how to govern the right hand when there ſhall be an occaſion to arm it for to ariſe fear in the Captain.</p>
            <p>To theſe mild and aged Mutineers, their General was their Glory, and their delight: But, had he been one hated by the ſeditious, or did they begin to loath and grow weary of the State that imploye; them (a State ſuppoſe declining too, which ſnatches and catches at all things as dying men do; or as thoſe do that are about ſuch; or be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t a State in ſwadling cloathes, whoſe tender roots facilitates its removall) how fierce and bold would theſe have then been? You would quickly have ſeen their daring forehead backt with a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hung tongue, and their audacities ſeconded by this language, not making their Addreſſes to the Commander, but encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another: Thus,</p>
            <p>We, whoſe victorious Swords uſ'd oft to give life to others, lets now give breath to our ſelves. Once ſuch was our love to the Cauſe, and liking to the Commander, that 'twas our wearineſs to be at reſt, and yet we repoſ'd in wearying our ſelves; 'twas our love to be upon duty, and we were in pain and labour, if that we labour'd not; we have been hitherto amorouſly ſeditious to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad every one the firſt place in dangers, and the laſt in repoſe, thus quarreling, to ſhew that love hath its civil Wars no leſs then hatred. But now the caſe is altered, and what thanks have we for all our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? we have been cajol'd, trapand, cheated, moulded, outed, diſplaced; fallacies and lyes are lookt upon as glorious arts, theſe are the State Stratagens, only they deſerve not that name becauſed uſed ſo often; we fight under Colours indeed, tis not ſubſtance; all promiſe, no performance: Where are our Arrears? muſt we that ſpend our lives for others rights be the firſt muſt be without our dues, and for our Conqueſts be made ſlaves in this to ſerve without pay? upon all deſigns how often have they promiſ'd us all that was behind, and muſt word be broke with us, who in honour ever keep it with an enemy? muſt they advance themſelves by keeping us low? Our Maſter <hi>Mountebanks</hi> makes no more of us then Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118620:5"/>we are cut and run through, while they vent their chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Balſomes, and thus heal and ſalve their own poverties, pretending to cure the grievances of the People. But our Arreers! Fellow-ſouldiers! Mony is our life; we may well keep a life for that, for which there's I one but ventures to looſe it. Mony! tis that that gives us ſtrength in the day of Battel; this Balſomes our ghaſtly wounds, and ſtocks our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſhed Veins with a better recruit then our own blood. Tis but honeſt then, and juſt for us tomutiny for that which makes all the World almoſt knaves; who ſhall call this ſedition? tis but a nobler way of petitioning for right, which our Grandees and Republicans have as often countenanc'd, as their deſigns had occaſions, tis they have taught us this abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable way of cure, to owe health to a diſeaſe, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to witcheraft. Come, the Camp's our common Pleas, and the Sword our Advocate; once Courts were held under Oakes, and we may as well keep them in the Field. Nor, need we fear, where the moſt are, all will be; in Lamps, the Oyl ſtill runs to that place that is burnt, and ſpirits to the part aggrieved. Come, if we can't over come, we can't be overcome.</p>
            <p>But indeed a diſcontended Army can never want matter whereby to vent its paſſion, eſpecially when they have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to disband, and find their rewards not anſwerable to their ſervice. <hi>Balaams</hi> dull Aſs in his own defence became a <hi>Demoſtheres.</hi> Had then a ſeditious body but a trooping Jeſuite for their mouth, that Spirit <hi>Legion,</hi> that enters into pay, with purpoſe to play the Divel in a State, how would his eloquence like Gunpowder ſet all on fire? how would his Rhetorick diſcover the unfortunateneſs of Souldiers, and the ungratefulneſs of thoſe that imploy them; who can't be thankful enough, doth uſually become unthankful; which is no better then a moral rebell. Beſides, the Souldier they cannot love, becauſe they fear him; for he that hath a Power to give, ſhews therein alſo a power to take away, which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſomewhat of that frightful word Superiority. But one may read a Souldiers deſtiny in the Heavens; wherein are Bears, Dog, Scorpion, Hydea, Goat (nay Caliſtus and Ariadne, who were not ſo honeſt as they ſhould be) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their feet is valiant <hi>Achilles</hi> placed, and other Demi-Gods.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118620:6"/>Sad fate, to ſee Beaſts and Monſters above Men, and they that have ventured higheſt to be loweſt ſet by. See the great <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> at laſt by a factious Senate thrown into exile. <hi>Scipio</hi> too, fon being too much regarded, became to be ill lookt upon: He who had conquered <hi>Africk</hi> the mother of Monſters, at his return found greater Monſters in <hi>Rome,</hi> accuſers that condemned him as guilty; of what? of that onely which makes Envy repining; and thus the great Commander baniſhes himſelf, changing his Sword into a Spade, his Horſe into Oxen, his Trenches into Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, his Victories into Harveſts; from a Souldier he turns Husbandman: No heading an Army now like to the Plough-tail. This advantage hath a great Mind above a great Heart.</p>
            <p>Ungratefull State! the very Tanker-bearers have their ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when they bedeck their Conduits with Garlands and Boughs, in thanks of the Water they draw from them. The Ocean too renders the received waters of the Rivers unto the Earth in miſts and Showers; and Kings by their Nobles return to the People all that they ſuckt from them: But Common-wealths-men, like thoſe two Monſters <hi>Soylla</hi> and <hi>Chanybdis,</hi> the one breaks the ſhip and ſcatters the lading, and the other ſwallows all up. Or perhaps this is learnt from the greaſie <hi>Dutch,</hi> who in his fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks firſt drinks the Glaſs and breaks it. Thus they of old ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Images of the Gods, and cared not for the Artificers that made them; thoſe Stones were honoured as Divine, and their Makers were trod upon as Stones. Or if it chance that the Intereſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> does do honour the Souldier, tis but as the Heathen did their Goddeſs Fever, that he may not be their Enemy. Alas! the Souldiers intereſt is the leaſt concerned, and the leaſt lookt after, who are onely made uſe of as ſtirrops to advance the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, and then they are thrown aſide, or tranſported abroad like old Iron. They ſeek to him onely for themſelves; for their own profit, not his good; juſt as we ſearch for Phyſical Herbs, not to make much of them, (though much be made of them,) but onely to chop and bruiſe and ſqueeze them, and all the good juyce and virtue being drawn out, as <hi>Coriſca</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Paſtor fido,</hi>
               <q>— they are ſtraight to the Dunghil thrown,</q>
So when they have done with us, with us they have done.</p>
            <p>Great Mens palates run after new diſhes, being ſoon cloy'd with the firſt. So the affections, which are the palate of the Soul,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118620:6"/>in our Governours quickly loath and nauſeate even that which foſter'd, nouriſh'd, and gave breſt to their Greatneſs. Nay, tis well if it ſtops here, ſince <hi>Nero</hi> ſcrupled not the murther of his Mother, that ſought all ways to raiſe him. We know too, that nurſing Fathers have had the like Fate, and ſome may fear that our mother Countrey will hardly ſcape their Anatomy.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee now a tongue can ſound to Arms, and with its Oyl put an edge to the Sword, and make it look young again; ſo that a Commander dreads more the witty Souldier, then the ſtrong one.</p>
            <p>But ſome one riſing againſt this, will ſay, That Sedition is reckon'd among the evil and wicked things, which ſcarce ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears how they conveniently ſhould know to be governed, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being one of thoſe, whoſe nature is no other then confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, diſturbance, immoderateneſs, in ſum, all that which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to Rule, Government and Order. Now admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that Sedition be an evil thing; I anſwer, that of many things that are evil, becauſe the end propoſed is evil, yet it cannot for all be ſaid, that they know not how to be rul d and govern'd, ſince they know fit and appoſite means for obtaining this end. <hi>Piſiſtratus</hi> was wicked, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> wicked in aſpiring to the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of their Countrey; yet in ſurmounting to the deſigned Poſt, none can deny, but that they knew moſt excellently how to govern themſelves. On the other ſide, who looks on <hi>Cicero,</hi> who endeavouring all wayes with the Senate to throw the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralſhip of the Army upon young <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> came to make him Monarch by the very ſame way, which he believ'd ought to have made him the renewer of the Republick; he, I ſay, may well affirm that he was a good man, but again he will ſubjoyn, that the good men are themſelves ſometimes governed unadviſedly. In like manner, I grant that Sedition ſounds in its title Confuſions, Quarrels, Revolutions; what then, ſhall not the Seditious know to be governed? This is falſe: And my Reaſon I will tell you, with an Example in my opinion moſt conducing. Sedition in an Army, is ſuch a thing, juſt as a Fever uſes to be in a mans body; for both are compounded of thoſe bad humours, which are working and fermenting to give aſſault againſt Head and Heart: Certainly, who looks upon this poor Ague-man, ſees nothing but diſcompoſures, turbations and confuſions, that are paſt repreſenting. He flings a thouſand ways his legs, his Arms,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118620:7"/>his hands about his bed, as if he deſired to fly, and to be rid of himſelf: His head goes to find his feet, and his feet riſe where his head was; the fire makes him deſire cold, and the cold makes him mad to run to the fire; he is weak, and his weakneſs forces him to marvellous violences; he rages, he languiſhes, he threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, he knows not what to ſay, and ſays more then he knows; he knows not what he ſees, and ſees not what's before his eyes; he is himſelf for his pain, and for feeling it, he is not himſelf. Who ever ſaw ſuch a <hi>Babel?</hi> And yet theſe inward and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Humours, which make the Sick-man not to rule himſelf, do ſo wonderfully govern themſelves in their aſſaults, that the <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> and <hi>Galens</hi> amazed cannot tell how theſe material and groſs Humours ſhould obſerve in their Paroxyſmes and fits ſuch exactneſs of days, and ſuch proportions of progreſſes, which would be enough to ſpring from a rational power, working by counſel and election. Nay for comfort to the Seditious, ſome will ſay, That an Ague too moſt an end will have its courſe, in ſpight of all Doctours, and their Jeſuites powder; beſides, that ſometimes 'tis Phyſick for a King.</p>
            <p>But here I find that <hi>Caeſar</hi> is againſt me. How (ſays he) can it be ever true, that Mutinies (even in their greateſt vigour) ſhould be governed with good rule, ſince that flying cloud, ſo proudly towring to ſee to, will diſſolve it ſelf at the leaſt breath; nay, at the firſt brow of the Majeſty of their General, they le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel and lay down their ſwellings for the moſt part: And this their Calm is their Shipwrack. Where was there a more enraged Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then when I returned out of Spain, which ſtirred up all my Armies Legions againſt me? Then with united and loud voices they required me to recompence with Money the Bloud they had loſt, or to grant them liberty to keep that which was remaining. They were ambitious too, to ſhew, that in War the Head depends more from the Hands, then the Hands do from the Head. Perhaps my men had not all the good qualities of an excellent Seditious; yet, they were ſuch old Souldiers, that their battels numbred all the Provinces of the Weſt, and 'twas their nature ever rather to fight, then diſcourſe; they would run into dangers with the ſame lookes that others came out of them; they were ſo ſtout, that I could ſee my Victories in their eyes, before ever a Sword drawn; they were of ſo much knowledge and wit too, that had I been leſs then I was, you might have ſeen
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118620:7"/>a glorious Army of all Commanders. And yet at the ſetled undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed undauntedneſs onely of my look, at the generous fire of my anger, and at the giving them my ſcornfull leave to disband; as if my eyes had been the nerves of their hands, and the edge of their ſwords, as if I had been able to move them with my beck, they all in ſpight of their teeth, trembling and mute, ran into the Camp, and yielded themſelves, and with one accord aſſured me, not onely their own hands to my fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture enterprizes, but for a preſent puniſhment offered their own throats. Thus Bees with animoſities enrag'd, caſt but a little duſt, they are ſtraight aſſwag'd. And ſhall we now ſay, that that is well governed, which fals to ground ſo eaſily? that order is good, which in an inſtant is diſcompoſed? that thoſe Wills are regularly directed toward their end, which in a moment change boldneſs into fear, force into weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and haughtineſs and fierceneſs into puſilanimity?</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Ceſar</hi> hath ſpoke as he Fought, Bravely and Galantly; yet I doubt not for all this fierce re-encounter but to keep the ſaddle: My reaſon this; To be eaſily changed from one eſtate into another, is not a ſign that that was not well grounded at the firſt, which is now changed. 'Tis a well manag'd Horſe on which the Cavalier with full carrear runs at the Ring; and yet but one light trip throws both him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Ruler over and over. Nay the Facility, after that the Sedition is ſpent, and the Souldiers turn to the obedience of their Commander, proves moſt ſtrongly, that it is beſt of all govern'd whilſt it continues. For the Souldiers then Revolting are put in a violent eſtate, it being their Natural to be quiet and complyant under obedience of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. Now 'tis very true, That things in a violent eſtate cannot hold long; yet therefore tis not true, That they cannot for that time they do hold be much better governed, then they would ever have been in their natural ſtate. This ariſes from that Inſtinct which is implanted in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, to deſire ſelf-conſervation: whence the greater the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are, the greater guard and warineſs is awakened in him that is in peril; and thereupon the violent State, arming all its forces againſt the being of a thing, is the cauſe that for its own ſafety, Head and Hands, Action and Councel are laid together to effect all how it may be beſt governed. Thus in the Water which is not our Sphere, one governs his Feet and Arms with a finer rule of motion, when he ſwims, then when he paſſes along in the water. So the fellow that dances on the Ropes, he balances himſelf perfectly, that neither eye nor hand, nor any part ſhall leane one tittle beyond the Cock or Poiſe; but after he is come down to the ground, he forms his ſteps by chance,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118620:8"/>and without any examination. And truly neither the one nor the other can ſtay in the Aire or Water long, ſo as upon the ground; yet one by his Swimming may arrive to what he intended to come to, and the Rope-dancer be a gainer by his perril.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Government. </seg>
               </label> But whileſt I conſent that ſedition is ſhort, I hardly may be thought to tell truth (which is my ſcope) if I ſhould overmuch enlarge my ſelf to treat thereof; ſince the truth of a Writing conſiſts in being conform'd to the nature of the thing whereof tis writ. Ile wind up therefore with this ſeaſonable advice, That ſedition cannot be counted ſuch an evil thing, where the action may produce any good. A bad tree cannot put forth good fruit. If Rebellion be the Law of Nature, which may juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it ſelf with a <hi>ſe defendendo;</hi> Mutiny ſure then may virtuouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand its dues or disbanding. He that bid the Souldier be content with his pay, did not bid him to be content without it. Nay, if Conſcience were a Military term, ſuppoſe that ſhould alter the mind, and make men ſee that horrid madneſs, which pluckt the Sun out of its Sphere, becauſe ſome men had ſore eyes. Where Sophiſtry and cheat hath made us go out of the way, tis lawfull to reſume and go back to our firſt Argument, and leave off thoſe errors, which others have made us guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of to conceal their own faults. The great Phyſitian retracted his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors concerning the ſutures of the head; and is it unjuſt for us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant thoſe about the diviſions, divorces, nay ſeparation of the Head. For Truth and Juſtice every ſtone may be ſtirr'd: The curing of thoſe that are bitten with <hi>Tarantulas,</hi> is to play ſo many tunes till they find the true one. That miſerable diſeaſe, called <hi>Hydrophobia,</hi> where the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is tormented both with thirſt, and fear of the water, his ſpeedy cure is to be flung over head and ears in the water; ſuch a ſort of Phyſick would heal our madneſs. You know my meaning. Since Fogs and Miſts are uſual in the counſels of Providence; ſomething may be ſometimes undertaken, where there is little encouragement. Tis not a ſhame to be overcome, where tis a ſin to overcome; nor is it unhandſome that any ſhould be ſubmitted to him, whom Law and Nature hath advanced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all. Conſider but <hi>Jupiters</hi> complaint to <hi>Menippus,</hi> That men ſince the upſtart and unknown Gods, they were diſreliſhed with him, ſo that he who formerly could hardly open his eys for the great ſmoak of the noble Hecatombs, now without any honour left, did almoſt die with hunger. See but what noble blood runs up and down begging and for god ſaking it almoſt, and compaſſing the earth to and fro, that they eat, not (as the Itinerant Devil or Miniſters ſo much propoſed) that they may devour. If you have not then abjur'd your Reaſon and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118620:8"/>and reſolv'd alſo to rebel againſt the Light, you cannot but face about, and be as you were, returning again to your old Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When we depart from a wonted Cuſtome, infallible <hi>Hippocrates</hi> tells us, our underſtanding is taken away. I do not here intend to be an Advocate of Monarchy; there is no ſuch Magnetiſm in my Reaſon, as to be able to draw Abettors, or to warp your affections to a cloſing with that Government: Yet fince you know the vergency and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Nation, whoſe heads are troubled becauſe they want their Head, it cannot but be your intereſt to ſide with them. Thus like <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> you may aſcend Heaven by your ſlaughter: otherwiſe you are but licenſed— to ſay Souldiers ſays all; and though you kill by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, yet you murder, becauſe you do it for Gain and Pay mſto, and make Religion but the Pander of your prey and plunder. Conſider then but our late Governors: One with the ſophiſtry of his tears, and arts of inſinuations, cajold and cheated all parties. The others, what <hi>Marriots</hi> of mens Eſtates have they been? Their covetous hungers were like the eating Ulcers or ſore legs that Beggars uſe to expoſe to us, which are uſually the worſe for our charity, or never the nearer mending. But what's become of theſe Legiſlators? You have pared off theſe Wens or Kings-evil of their Countrey, (for ſo <hi>Tully</hi> calls vile and inconſiderate men,) and this collection of Humours you have worthily diſcuſſed, becauſe they would not draw to a head. As <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>A ſtorm hath hurled them out of their place:</hi> They were dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth from among men, who cried after them as after a thief, and hiſt theſe Saltim-banks off of their Stage. Give me leave now to talk a little Scripture to you, who think you have the Monopoly of holineſs, and count your ſelves of the ſect of the Saints. You know how <hi>Aſa</hi> was cenſured for relying upon the Phyſicians, when he ſhould have applied himſelf to his Lord. So the Bloud-iſſue woman ſpent all upon them, and had ſpent more perhaps, if ſhe had had more to ſpend; yet ſhe could never be well untill ſhe laid hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord. No doubt theſe State-leeches that you ſo much idoll'd, cannot heal our diſtempers. Theſe Excellentiſſims, whom ye ador'd and lookt on as the All-heal, the Altaheſt, and univerſal Medicine: theſe have been the bane, the poyſon, and ruine of the Nation. A Parliament of late days being but <hi>Pandora</hi>'s Box, iſſuing out our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, and miſeries, and woes. They are all Phyſicians of no value. Tis your true Lord that muſt be entertain'd and embraced, and he will remedy all; tis he alone that will heal the grievances of all, but thoſe that have deſir'd rather <hi>Eſau</hi>'s bleſſing to ſhake off the yoke.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118620:9"/>
            <p>For popular Government, let him that deſires that form ſet it up firſt in his own family; there can be nothing but confuſion therein, ſince the people underſtand not reaſon, and for authority and perſwaſions they diſpiſe it; <hi>vox Populi vox Dei,</hi> was never underſtood of Iſonomy or levelling. I think I ſpeak no Riddles: yet I am not of that Church, whoſe Intereſt tis ſaid deſires moſt a King. I will not diſpute that point, but I much ſuſpect it: A Loyoliſt ſure can never be Loyal, and they that have given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to their conduct cannot wiſh cordially the Royal return. Confuſions in the State is meat and drink to them, who <hi>Nero</hi>-like are well pleaſed to warm themſelves at our ruins. Hence they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their name from Jeſus, becauſe they alſo came into the World not to ſend Peace, but the Sword; to ſet Kingdomes on fire, or to prolong the flames, not to extinguiſh and out them; whence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the foreſeeing God-father chriſtned their Founder <hi>Ignatius.</hi> Obſerve ſince ſo much of the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> hath been powred in upon us, have not the Waters gone over our head, and ſtruck it off too? what a deſign and deſtruction, and even abominable deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion happened upon us? See what garboils and diviſions they wrought in the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> where tis ſaid too, that they divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the very Boys, not ſo much by their inſtructions, as their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. Think we to thrive better? Beſides how can theſe deſign or work for the regal Reſtauration, who undoubtedly comes not in without his Clergy. That Clergy is the ſalt of the earth, and the throwing down this ſalt hath been the occaſion of all our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, and the reaſon too that the God of flies hath blown and tainted here all fleſh almoſt with Hereſies, Villanies, and Rebellion. But I have done: You have my Mite, which I hope may be as acceptable to you as Taxes: If the diſcourſe hath any countenance of reaſon, look not you with a bad one upon it. I go not about to decoy you into your loſs; my drift is your glory and your good, who ſince you have been counted their Journy-men and Hirelings, 'tis but juſt you ſhould look out for the beſt Wages. Now to do good to give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> what is his, and to do as you would be done unto; theſe are things by which you will gain moſt. Thus you may merit a Crown above, and the White Robe, which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter far, then a Red <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oat.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
